A Guide to the Cary Family Papers, 1748-1772
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Cary Family Papers, 1748-1772
Library of Virginia
21434
6 leaves and 12 p.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Purchased from M.P. Harrison, 2016 West Grace Street, Richmond, Virginia, 14 September 1938.
Biographical/Historical Information
The Cary family arrived in Virginia when Miles Cary (1623-1667) of Bristol, England, immigrated to Warwick County about 1645, establishing the family home at "The Forest." Miles Cary's grandson, Henry Cary (ca. 1675-1749) moved to Henrico County in 1730, establishing his home "Ampthill" south of the James River in that part of Henrico County which became Chesterfield County. His son Archibald Cary (1721-1787) extended the family holdings in Chesterfield County and into Buckingham, Cumberland, Albemarle, and Goochland Counties. He extended the Cary family manufacturing concerns to include not just the family mill, but also a furnace and foundry. Archibald Cary held offices in county government, including justice of the peace, and he served in the Virginia conventions of 1775 and 1776. A friend of George Washington, Cary supported the colonial cause during the Revolution with his time and money. Cary served as speaker of the Virginia Senate from 1776 to his death in 1787.
Scope and Content Information
Chesterfield County County records, 1748-1772, consisting of will of Henry Cary (ca. 1675-1749) of Henrico and Chesterfield Counties, and release from Elizabeth Cary (d. 1751) to Archibald Cary (1721-1787), both of Chesterfield County. Also includes deeds for 1,000 acres and 644 acres from William Byrd III (1728-1777); deed for 1000 acres from David Bell (ca. 1716-1806) and Judith Bell (1726-1798); deed for 736 acres from Benjamin Watkins (ca. 1725-1781); and deed for 240 acres from Seth Ward (d. 1772) all to Archibald Cary. Also contains a bond, power of attorney, and a deed for slaves from Alexander Speirs to Cary.
Contents List
- Will (copy). Henry Cary, Henrico County, 27 May 1784., 5 p.
- Release. Elizabeth Cary to Archibald Cary, 7 April 1750., 1 p.
- Bond. Alexander Speirs to Archibald Cary, 20 July 1750., 1 p.
- Power of attorney. Alexander Speirs to Archibald Cary and James Barnes, 20 July 1750., 2 p.
- Deed. William Byrd, "Westover," Charles City County, to Archibald Cary, Chesterfield County, 1,000 acres in Chesterfield County, dated and recorded, 1 June 1853., 2 p.
- Deed (damaged). David Bell and Judith, his wife, to Archibald Cary, both parties of Chesterfield County, 1,000 acres in Albemarle County, 18 October 1755., 2 p.
- Deed. Benjamin Watkins to Archibald Cary, both parties of Chesterfield County, 736 acres in Chesterfield County, dated 3 October 1760 and recorded Chesterfield County, 7 November 1760., 2 p.
- Deed. Alexander Speirs, Glasgow, [Scotland], to Archibald Cary, Chesterfield County, certain Negroes, dated 1 October 1760 and recorded Chesterfield County, February 1761., 1 p.
- Deed. William Byrd, Charles City County, to Archibald Cary, Chesterfield County, 644 acres in Chesterfield County, dated 2 May 1770 and recorded Chesterfield County, October 1771., 2 p.
- Deed (damaged). Seth Ward to Archibald Cary, both parties of Chesterfield County, certain land in Chesterfield County, 25 December 1772, 2 p.